French Literature mss., LMC 1391 LMC 1391
Lilly Library
French Literature mss.
ca. 1750-1977
Lilly Library
LMC 1391
6 folios
1 bound
2 Boxes 2 standard
Consists of individual items acquired separately either as a gift or purchased from a variety of sources, relating to or by French literary figures. Additions continue to be made.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Acquisition Information
Received from various sources at various times. Accession information is given with the item entry. The most recent additions made in 2004.
Scope and Content Note
Consists of a collection of items received singly or in small groups from various sources at various times, which were not kept together as a distinct collection.
Note on Indexing Term - "Art": Of particular interest are 1917 L'Homme et Son Desir: poeme plastique by Paul Claudel with a collage by Audrey Parr; two drawings by Jean Cocteau from 1920 and 1929 and two drawings in blue pencil by Genevieve Asse.
For digitized content, see Digital Collections.
Arrangement/Organization
Arranged chronologically. Undated items are arranged alphabetically at the end of the series.
French literature --18th century.; French literature --19th century.; French literature --20th century.; French poetry --18th century.; French poetry --19th century.; French poetry --20th century.; Bookbinding --France.; France --History --Revolution, 1789-1799; France --History --July Revolution, 1830.; Theater --France.; French drama--Translations into English; Leprosy.; Women --Education.; Art; French Literature; Lilly, Josiah Kirby, 1893-1966, former owner.; Baudelaire, Charles, 1821-1867.; Claudel, Paul, 1868-1955.; Cocteau, Jean, 1889-1963.; Croix-Rouge franðcaise.; Dumas, Alexandre, 1802-1870.; Farrère, Claude, 1876-1957.; Flaubert, Gustave, 1821-1880.; Hugo, Victor, 1802-1885.; Leconte, Sébastien-Charles, 1865-1934.; Legion d'honneur (France); Louis IX, King of France, 1214-1270 --Poetry.; Miguel, André, 1920-; Morand, Paul, 1888-1976.; Proust, Marcel, 1871-1922.; Régnier, Henri de, 1864-1936.; Verne, Jules, 1828-1905.; Voltaire, 1694-1778.; Zola, Émile, 1840-1902.
- French Literature mss.
  Scope and Contents
  Arranged chronologically at the item level, undated items are further arranged alphabetically
  - Voltaire, François Marie Aroutet, 1694-1778, author. La Religion naturelle. Poème en 4 chants par M. de Voltaire. A.D.S., 1752; [31] p. 22 cm.
    Scope and Content
    In black ink.
    Begins with a 2 p. dedication: "au roi de Prusse."
    Folios tied together with white ribbon.
    Carries some corrections and additions in another 18th century hand.
    Accompanied by A.D., 1 p., 17.5 cm., explaining the manuscript.
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Provenance: From the archives of Madame Dupin; collection Montgermont (Paris, 17 May, 1941)
    Purchase. 1989
  - Voltaire, François Marie Aroutet, 1694-1778, author. To "mon divin ange" Charles Augustin de Ferriol, comte d'Argental. Complains that troubles encountered through recent property acquisitions have delayed work on "les chaveliers et les czars." A.L., 1759; 7, Nov 1941; 7, Nov 1941.; 1 p. 15.6 cm.
    Published with commentary by Henry H.H. Remak in Modern Language Notes, LXI, 7, Nov 1941.
    Gift. 1982
  - Palissot de Montenoy, Charles, 1730-1814, dramatist. Argenteuil, France. To Ponce Denis Écouchard Le Brun. Sous-Carrierre, [France?]. Praises his work. Will visit soon and hopes to officiate at the chapel there. A.L.S., 1769 July 16; [3] p. 21.7 cm.
    In French.
    Gift. 1984
  - Palissot de Montenoy, Charles, 1730-1814, dramatist. Argenteuil, France. To Ponce Denis Écouchard Le Brun. Paris. Encourages him to publish his poetry so that public may not be deprived of his talent. Expresses concern that his works are being plagarized. A.L.S., 1769 Dec 27; [3] p. 22 cm.
  - Eighteenth-century feminist manuscript. Omelettes ou l'origine des Nouvelles Amazones. Ouvrage peu analogue à son titre, mais qui dit plus qu'il n'annonce. Divisé en chants puisque c'est un Poème. Par l'Auteur qui se soucie fort peu qu'on le connoisse. L'an de Grace et de disgrace 1773.; imprimé nulle part, puisqu'il ne mérite pas de l'être. Première et Dernière Édition. Prix: la peine de le lire. A most amusing mock-heroic verse satire on contemporary sexual mores. The saga recounts the tragic decline of amorous arts being foiled by the Goddess Discord by means of a treacherous omelette; and the final revenge of women in the formation of a new society of Amazons. Written out in a fine, flowing script with a hand-painted vignette on the title-page showing two men eating an omelette. This title is not listed in Gay-Lemonnyer and is probably unpublished., Octavo. 86pp. Bound in full contemporary calf with triple gilt rule. Spine gilt in six compartments. 19cm.
    Purchase. 1991
  - Lebret, M.. To Monsieur, regarding Voltaire and Cramer., 1774 Apr 14; 2 p. 23.5 cm.
    Purchase. 1982
  - Alembert, Jean le Rond d', 1717-1783, mathematician, philosopher. To Jeremy Bentham. Lincoln's Inn, London. He has received the two works Bentham sent him as well as Bentham's letter, for which he thanks him. A.L.S., 1778 Jun 26; 2 p. 21.7 cm.
    Addresses from address leaf.
  - Genlis, Stéphanie Félicité Ducrest de Saint Aubin, comtesse de, 1746-1830, author. Lioré. To L'abbé Faurier. Writes to him about his discontent and his wish to leave for Paris; that the princes and Mademoiselle are no longer small children. A.L.S., 1786 Jun 14; 2 p. 15 cm.
    Addressee given on integral leaf.
    Purchase. 1977
  - Commonplace book of French verse recorded by an unknown writer. A.D., 18th cent.; 159 p. 10 cm. Bound.
    The date 1777 in reference to a verse is noted on page 135.
    Table of Contents.
    Contains selections from several sources including Voltaire, Maréchal, Beaumarchais, Boufflers, and Gentil-Bernard, mostly on women and wine, many giving the air to be used.
    Gift. 1973
  - Extrait d'un journal critique sur les poemes. A.N., 18th cent.; 1 leaf 16 cm.
    Holograph notes from an unidentified journal criticizing the poem of Pierre Le Moyne,1602-1671, on Saint Louis with reference to Book XIII, and mentioning Voltaire.
    Removed from Le Moyne, Saint Louvys… poeme heroiqve. Paris, A. Covrbe, 1658 (Lilly PR18178 .L47S3). 1974
  - Béranger, Pierre Jean de, 1780-1857, poet. To Pierre Jean David d'Angers. Quai de la Mégisserie No. 56. Comments on an illustration by Maurin… "un tableau historique. ce n'est plus lá ma modeste vivandière; c'est une figure bien autrement bell…". A.L.S., 1820 Mar 1; 4 p. 18.8 cm.
    Accompanied by copy of typed transcription and other information about the letter.
    Gift. 1983
  - Hugo, Victor Marie comte, 1802-1885, novelist. To comte Bernard Marie Jules de Ressegiuer, Place St. Etienne, á Toulouse. Discusses matters of common interest and says his new address will be "rue du dragon, no. 30." A.L.S., 1822 Apr 3; 1 p. 20 cm.
    French.
    Top third of letter removed.
    With attached cover of addressee.
    Removed from Academie des Jeux Floraux, Toulouse, Recuiel de l'Academie des jeux floraux. Toulouse, M.-J. Dalles, 1818-1821 (Lilly PQ 3807 .T7A32). 1973
  - Fourier, François Marie Charles, 1772-1837, social reformer. Lyons, France. To Monsieur Saint Olive, Jeune. Lyons, France. Comments on his work Traité de l'association… and other writings "Sous peu je ferai paraitre un petit abrégé qui m'est demande en Angleterre…" A.L.S., 1829 Sept 16?; 2 p. 26.5 cm.
    Removed from Fourier, François Marie Charles, Traité de l'association demestique-agriocle, Paris: Bossage, 1822 (Lilly HX704 .F775T7). 1977
  - Murger, Henri, 1822-1861, novelist. Malfilâtre. A.D.S., 1839 Sept 25; 3 leaf. 27 cm.
    In honor of Jacques Charles Louis Clinchamp de Malfilâtre, 1732-1767, poet.
    Six stanzas of 8 lines each.
    Introduced by quotation from Gilbert, "La faim mit au tombeau Malfilâtre ignoré."
    Purchase. 1972
  - Dumas, Alexandre, 1802-1870, author. To "Monsieure Le Ministre." Requests permission for the continued performance of his play Antony at the Théatre de la Porte Saint-Martin. A.L.S., ca. 1840; 1 p. 26.8 cm.
    Removed from Dumas, Antony:… Paris: A. Auffray, 1831 (Lilly PQ2225 .A7). 1980
  - Balzac, Honré de, 1799-1850, novelist. To [Denis Hippolyte] Souverain. Concerns the preface of Une Tenebreuse affaire. A.L.S., 1841 Dec ?; 1 p. 15 cm.
    Letter signed as from "de Bc."
    Letter is undated but has been assigned a probable date of Dec. 1841 or Jan 1842 in its publication in Balzac, Correspondence, Tome IV, 1840-Avril 1845, Paris, Editions Garnier Fréres, 1966 (PQ2179 .A2 1960 V.4), page 373.
    Removed from Balzac, Une Tenebreuse affaire, Paris, M. Hippolyte Souverain, 1842 (Lilly PQ2173 .T2). 1973
  - Sand, George, 1804-1876, author. To Monsieur Perrotin, rue de las fontaine Moliere, 41, Paris. Concerns references for M. Scribe and concludes "Chopin et Maurice vous donnet bon shake-hands. Puisque vous voila anglais, vous comprenez." A.L.S., 1845 Jul 7; 3 p. 21 cm.
    Embossed with initials G.S.
    Purchase. 1973
  - Hugo, Victor Marie, comte, 1802-1885, novelist. To Jean Pons Guillaume Viennet. Solicits aid for "M. Pommier, ancien rédacteur d'un journal de Lyon." A.L.S., 1847 Jul 28; 1 p. 21 cm.
    Bears the blue stamp of Société des Gens Lettres.
    Published in Hugo, Correspondence. Paris, Albin Michael, 1952, Vol. 4, page 205 (PQ2279 .A2)
    Bound in Hugo, L'Aumône. Rouen, Nicetas Periaux, 1830 (Lilly PQ2285 .A9). 1980
  - Barbier, Auguste, 1805-1882, poet. To Jean Bernard Lafon, called Mary-Lafont [i.e. Mary-Lafon]. "… j'ai l'honneur de vous envoyer le volume ci-joint. C'est de tous mes ouvrages celui que le publie a le plus favorablement accueilli…" A.L.S., 1848 Dec 22; 1 p. 21 cm.
    Integral address leaf bears name of recipient who is also identified as "Archivisite de la Société des gens de lettres.
    Tipped in between half title and title page of Barbier, Iambes et poèmes. Paris: Paul Masgana, 1841 (Lilly PQ2189 .B33 I13 1841). 1985.
  - Renan, Ernest, 1823-1892, philosopher. Paris, France. To Auguste Morel. Writes of criticisms on his book, Averroes… of working at the library, and of taking a vacation in the near future. A.L.S., 1852 Aug 27; 3 p. 21 cm.
    Removed from Ernest Renan, Averroes et l'averroisme: essai historique, Paris: Auguste Durand, 1852 (Lilly B749 .Z7r4). 1978
  - Musset, Louis Charels Alfred de, 1810-1857, poet. To Mon cher ami. Has spent the entire night rewriting his verses. A.L.S., 1853 Jan 14; 1 p. 21 cm.
  - Dumas, Alexandre, 1802-1870, playwright, novelist. "Accepte pour six cent quatre vingt cinq francs au 15 fevrier 1853." A.D.S., 1853 Feb 15; 1 leaf 24 cm.
    Paper watermarked with shadow border, date and initials.
    Removed from Dumas, Catherine Howard, Paris, Charpentier, 1834 (Lilly PQ2225 .C25). 1975
  - Goncourt, Edmond Louis Antoine Huot de, 1822-1896, author. To [Jean François Barrière]. Thanks him for the review of the book in Journal des Debats. A.L.S., 1854 Apr 18; 1 p. 20.5 cm.
    Signed: E. et Jules Alfred Huot de Goncourt, apparently in the hand of Edmond de Goncourt.
    Removed from Edmond et Jules de Goncourt, Histoire de la société française pendant la Révolution. Paris: E. Dentu, 1854 (Lilly DC33.5 .G63 Vault). 1977
  - Lamartine, Alphonse Marie Louis de, 1790-1869, poet. Monceau, France. To "monsieur." Expresses his sympathy. Will be in Paris in three weeks and will talk with him then. A.L.S., 1854 Dec 11; [2] p. 20.5 cm.
  - Merimée, Prosper, 1803-1870, novelist. Cannes Hotel de la Poste. To Leon François Raymond Pillet. Comments on the countryside and mentions the names of Lord Londesborough, Lady Ashburton, David Brewster, and Lady Shelley. A.L.S., 1856 Dec 19; 2 p. 21 cm.
    Accompanied by a letter dated June 25, 1937, from a French dealer who established the year and the recipient of the letter.
  - Flaubert, Gustave, 1821-1880, novelist. Madame Bovary errata. A.D., 1857; 3 p. 35 cm. (Bound Vault 2)
    Vault 1.
    Bound in green morocco.
    Original holograph manuscript of errata present in the first edition of Madame Bovary.
    From the library of Josiah Kirby Lilly, Jr., Indianapolis, IN. 1956
  - Saint-René-Taillandier, René Gaspard Ernest, 1817-1879, historian. Montpellier, France. To "Monsieur et ami." Recounts the final days and funeral arrangements of poet and mutual friend Auguste Brizeux. A.L.S., 1858 May 8; [4] p. 21 cm.
    Tipped in before half title page of Brizeux, Les Bretons. Paris: Paul Masgana, 1845. (Lilly PQ2201 .B67 B84 1845) 1991
  - Baudelaire, Charles Pierre, 1821-1867, poet. Fantòmes parisiens. A.D., 1859 June.; 2 leaves. 20 cm.
    Author's signature has been clipped from another manuscript and pasted to the verso of the first leaf, signed "Tout à vous Ch. Baudelaire."
    From the adjunct second leaf ¼ of the lower part has been cut off.
    Written on the verso of the second leaf is a portion of a letter to an unnamed correspondent who has been idenitifed as Jean Morel, directeur of la Revue francaise.
    Both poem and letter are undated but published under the assigned date of June, 1859, in Oeuvres Completes de Charles Baudelaire par M. Jacques Crepet (Paris, Editions Louis Conard) 1947, vol. 13, pages 321-324 (PQ2191 .A1 1923).
    Poem first published in La Revue Contemporaine, September 15, 1859.
    Significant variations from version published as "Les Sept Viellards" in the second edition of Les Fleurs du Mal in 1861 (Lilly PQ2191 .F6 1861).
    Formerly in the library of Victor Meric.
    Purchase. 1976
  - Notes in several unidentified hands related to Recueil de pièces authentiques servant a l'historire de la révolution à Strasbourg… by Andreas Ulrich published in 1795. A.Ds., 1859-1902; 27 p. 5-28 cm.
    Sixteen pieces dated: 28.2.59; [1861?]; 27.9.81 (with later appended date of 22.1.1902); 25.12.90; 6.8.91; 7.1.91; [1891?]; 19.4.93 (2 items); 20.4.93; 24.11.95; 27.4.96; 3.11.99; 14.4.99 (verso of printed birth announcement of M. & Mme. G. Lauth, 11 Mars 1899); 14.3.1901.
    Removed from Ulrich, Recueil de pièces authentiques servant a l'historire de la révolution à Strasbourg… Strasbourg, Chez André Ulrich, 1795 (Lilly DC195 .S8U45 1795). 1978
  - Durand, Auguste, 1801-1877, publisher. Paris, [France]. To Monsieur Langlois. Letter of thanks. A.L.S., 1863 Dec 5 [?]; 1 p. 21 cm.
    Removed from Vol. I of Jean Lebeuf, Histoire de la Ville et de Tout le Diocèse de Paris. Paris, Auguste Durand, 1863 (DC707 .L44). 1955
  - Erckmann, Emile, 1822-1899 and Chatrian, Alexandre, 1826-1890. Paris, [France]. To Marc Fournier., 1864 Sept 16; 1 p. 20.5 cm.
    Removed from Erckmann, Emile and Chatrian, Alexandre, Madame Therese.. Paris, J.Hetzel, 1863 (Lilly PQ2238 .M17). 1980
  - Renan, Ernest, 1823-1892, philosopher Sèvres, France. To Cher Monsieur. Asks to send him three or four copies of Langues se critiquer. A.L.S., 1866 Aug 3; 1 p. 20 cm.
    Received date: August 6.
    Watermark: Lacroix Frères.
    Removed from Ernest Renan, L'abesse de Jouarre, Paris: Calman Lévy, 1866 (Lilly PQ2386 .R37A6). 1978
  - Hugo, Victor Marie, comte, 1802-1885, novelist. Hauteville House, [France]. To [Albert Lacroix.] Asks that a copy of Les Travailleurs de la Mer be given Mr. Gill. A.L.S., 1867 May 22; 1 p. 13 cm.
    From the library of Josiah Kirby Lilly, Jr., Indianapolis, IN 1956
  - Feuillet, Octave, 1821-1890, author. To "Monsieur." Concerns the reestablishment of telegraphic communications. A.L.S., 1870 Nov 28; 1 p. 17 cm.
    Gift. 1961
  - Massenet, Jules Emile Frederic, 1842-1912. Qu'il me soit permis de remercier... les excellents artistes... Marie Laurent... from Les Erinnyes., 1873 Jan 6; 1 p. 19 cm.
    Removed from Jules Emile Frederic Massenet, Les Erinnyes, Paris: A. Lemerre, 1873 (Lilly ML50.M41 E72) 1981
  - Labiche, Eugène, 1815-1888, playwright. Note authorizing Mr. Langneau to perform Labiche's play, L'affaire de la rue de Louricine A.D.S., 1873 Mar 6; 1 p. 13.1 cm.
    On embossed, E L, paper.
    Removed from Labiche, L'affaire de la rue de Louricine, Paris: Michel Lévy frères, 1857 (Lilly PQ2321 .A67) 1991
  - Richepin, Jean, 1849-1926, writer. Le Corsaire Journal politique quotidien, 123 Rue Montmartre, [Paris, France]. To "Cher Maitre." Writes about his book La chanson des gueux which is going to appear the next Friday. A.L.S., 1876 May 17; 2 p. 21 cm.
    Removed from Jean Richepin, La chanson des gueux, Paris: Librairie Illustrée, 1876 (Lilly PQ2387 R4 C5). 1977
  - Richepin, Jean, 1849-1926, writer. To "Cher Maitre." Thanks for writing a good review on his book, La chanson des gueux, and complimentary remarks. A.L.S., 1876 May 25; 1 p. 21 cm.
    Removed from Jean Richepin, La chanson des gueux, Paris: Librairie Illustrée, [1876] (Lilly PQ2387 R4 C5). 1977
  - Zola, Émile, 1840-1902, author. Bibliothèque Charpentier, 13, Rue de Grenell-St.-Germain, Paris. To "mon cher ami." Requests that enclosed note be published in the recipient's literary news. A.L.S., 1881 Jun 14; 1 p. 20.5 cm.
    Enclosure not present.
    Removed from Zola, Nos auteurs dramatiques. Paris: Charpentier, 1881 (Lilly PQ2511 .N55 copy 2). 1982
  - Spoelberch de Lovejoul, Charles Victor Maximilien Albert, vicomte de, 1836-1907, bibliographer. Bruxelles, Belgium. To "monsieur." Thanks him for the information concerning the autographs he is selling. Asks whether he has any of Gautier, Balzac, or George Sand. A.L.S., 1882 Dec 23; [4] p. 12.8 cm.
    Removed from Spoelberch de Lovenjoul, Histoire des oeuvres de H. de Balzac. Paris C. Lévy, 1888 (Lilly PQ2181 .S7 1888). 1981
  - Zola, Emile, 1840-1902, author. Medan. To "Mon cher confrere." Deals with Germinal and translations of it. A.L.S., 1884 Oct. 18; 2 p. 21 cm.
    Addressee has been identified as Ernst Ziegler, translator of Germinal for the German market.
    From the library of Josiah Kirby Lilly, Jr. Indianapolis, Indiana 1956
  - Bourget, Paul Charles Joseph, 1852-1935, novelist, critic. Milan, Italy. To Philip Gille. Expresses his appreciation for the review of Cruelle Enigme in Figaro. A.L.S., 1885 Feb 6; 1 p. 20 cm.
    Mounted in Bourget, Cruelle Enigme. Paris, Alphonse Lemerre, 1885 (Lilly PQ2199 .C95). 1974
  - Verne, Jules, 1828-1905, author. To M. A. Arnold. "Monsieur, Voici, en français, les compliment. Je votre tres obligè scriviteur." A.N.S., 1885 May 4; 1 p. 8 cm.
    Source unknown. Transferred from Lilly Library Administrative Office. 1975
  - France, Anatole, 1844-1924, author. Leaf from Nos Enfants. A.D., 1885 June 1; 1 leaf. 20 cm.
    First two sentences are identical with those published on page 14 of France, Nos Enfants... Paris, Librairie Hachetts et Cie, 1887.
    The remaining two sentences differ in content and structure and mention the names of Pauline and Claudine.
    Leaf bears the number 4 in black ink in the upper right corner and the number 8 in blue crayon at the top of the mss.
    The initials SM in blue crayon are located in the center of the leaf.
    Removed from the above named edition of Nos Enfants (Lilly PQ2254 .N88). 1975
  - Rollinat, Maurice, 1846-1903, poet. to "Monsieur." "J'ai été très sensible à la délicate attention que vous avez eue de me témoigner votre sympathie littéraire…" A.L.S., 1885 June.; 1 p. 17.5 cm.
    Tipped in following title page.
    In Rollinat, Les névroses. Paris: G. Charpentier, 1883.(Lilly PQ2388.R428 N4) 1987
  - Banville, Théodore de, 1823-1891, author. To "mon cher collaborateur." Refers to Georges Rochegrosse and M. Lavaissirère. A.L.S., 1886 Feb 4; 1 p. 16 cm.
    Removed from Banville, Les cariatides. Paris, Pilout, editeur, 1842 (Lilly PQ2187 .C27). 1974
  - Beque, Henry François, 1837-1899, dramatist. To Philippe Deforges. Au Ministre de Beaux Arts, rue de Valois, Paris. Refers to Becque's book Michel Pauper. A.L.S., 1887 Apr 15; 1 p. 18 cm.
    Accompanied by cover.
    Date taken from postmark.
    Removed from Becque, Michel Pauper. Paris: Tresse & Stock, 1887 (Lilly PQ2193 .B4 M62) 1974
  - Coppée, François, 1842-1908, poet, playwright. Sonnet entitled Sur la "Vestale"… & Henri Lefort. A.D., 1887 May.; 1 leaf. 22 cm.
    In ink.
    Penciled note states "Sonnet intime & poeme inedit."
    Mounted in Coppée, Le Passant. Paris, Armand Magnier, 1897 (Lilly PQ2211 .C3P28 1897). 1974
  - Bergson, Henri Louis, 1859-1941, philosopher. Clermont-Ferrand, France. To Albert Kahn. 102 Rue Richliueu, Paris, France. Writes of staying at Clermont to work on his thesis and he wants to know all the news. A.L.S., 1888 Jan 1; 2 p. 18 cm.
    Accompanied by envelope.
    Removed from Henri Louis Bergson, Essai sur les données immédiates de la conscience: thése pour le doctorat, Paris: Félix Alcan, 1889 (Lilly B2430 .B4 E53). 1977
  - Agar-Marye, Mme Florence Leonide (Charvin), (Mme George Marye), 1836-1891, actress. To Sarah Bernhardt. Comments on Le Passant of François Coppée. A. copy, 1888 Feb 24; 6 p. 28 cm.
    Holograph copy in the hand of G. Mouravit, with appended commentary by Mouravit. This is not the Gustave Mouravit born in 1840. Published in L'Amateur d'Autograph, Nov., 1907, p. 304.
    Bound in Coppée, Le Passant. Paris. Armand Magnier, 1897 (Lilly PQ2211 .C3P28 1897). 1974
  - Cherrier, Henri, 1839-, bibliographer. 44, Rue du Louvre, 44, Paris. To "mon cher collègue." Explains that Les mariages de Paris does not include a list of members of the firm because the book was printed before he was informed that such a list is customary., 1888 Mar 8
    Mourning stationary.
    Removed from Edmond François Valentin About, Les mariages de Paris. Paris: imprimé pour les Amis de Livres par A. Lahure, 1887 (Lilly PQ2151 .M33). 1980
  - Barrés, Maurice, 1862-1923, writer, politician. To d'Orfer. Discusses promotion of his latest book in newspapers where reviews or advertisements could appear. A.L.S., 1889 Aug 25; [8] p. 16.5 cm.
    Removed from Barrés, Anatole France. Paris: Charavay Frères, 1883 (Lilly PQ2254 .Z5B272). 1980.
  - Oliver, Arsène, -1895, author. To [?] His brochure Avisol. A.L.S., 1890 Jun 2; 2 p. 21 cm.
    Mounted in Olivier's… Avisol… Paris, Baudry et Cie, 1889. (Lilly TL 654 .O6A35) 1959
  - Verne, Jules, 1828-1905, author. Amiens, France To [?] Believes that the voyage around the world could be made in 60 days. A.L.S., 1890 Jun 6; 1 p. 12 cm.
    Framed.
    Gift. 1939
  - Regnier, Henri François Joseph de, 1864-1936, poet. La Lobbe par Wasigny, Ardennes. To Cher Monsieur. Accepts the invitation to collaborate with Albert Mockel in editing the review Wallonie. A.L.S., 1890 Sept 7; 3 p. 18 cm.
  - Goncourt, Edmond Louis Antoine Huot de, 1822-1896, author. Rue Pierre-Guerin, Paris, France. To Madame Sichel Dulong. 69 rue d'amsterdam, Paris, France. "Trois jours passés…" A.Card S., 1893 Dec 25; 8 cm.
    Message of six lines written on "Cart – Telegramme Response."
    Removed from Edmond et Jules de Goncourt, Préfaces et manifestes littéraitres, Paris: G. Charpentier et Cie., 1888 (Lilly PQ 2261 .P923). 1977.
  - Regnier, Henri François Joseph, de, 1864-1936, poet. To Georges Khnopff, 1 Rue Saint Bernard, Chaussee de Charleroi, Bruxelles, Belgigue. Hopes to see Khnopff at the Taverne du Globe in Brussels about the portrait. A.L.S., 1894 Feb 15; 2 p. 18 cm.
    Stationary bordered in black.
    Accompanied by envelope bordered in black with blue wax seal.
    Date taken from envelope.
  - Estaunié, Édouard, 1862-1942, author. Paris. To Monsieur. Accepts with pleasure the reproduction of "l'Emprinte" offered to him in the letter of the 26th past. A.L.S., 1894 Oct 28; 1 p. 17.7 cm.
    Removed from Estaunié, Le Silence dans la campagne. Paris, Perrin et cie, 1926 (Lilly PQ2609 .S8S58). 1980.